so let's look at what one memory bit
looks like in SRAM and dram technology
the bit sits at the intersection of a
word line that passes by many bits and a
bit line that also passes by many bits
so a memory is a matrix of cells like
this and theem will also have a word
line and a bit line what the word line
does is it controls a transistor here
that can open or close itself to connect
the cell to the bit line so the idea is
that if we want to access this cell we
activate this word line which opens this
transistor and now the memory cell is
connected to the bit line so if we want
to write data we put the bit line at the
value we want and the cell gets that
value if we want to read the data we let
go of the bit lines and then the cell
here will get a new value on the bit
line so we can sense what it is in SRAM
the actual memory cell consist consists
of two inverters each inverter has two
transistors that's how you build an
inverter and the idea is that if this is
one here then this inverter flips it and
outputs a zero here this other inverter
flips that and outputs one here so once
we disconnect this transistor this cell
will keep its value it's going to
maintain a zero here because that zero
is inverted and output as a one here
which amplifies this Zer here so we have
a feedback loop here that keeps the data
that we want so how do we write to this
cell so if we try to put a one here this
inverter here is working against us
because it says a one it wants to Output
a zero and the answer to that is that
this transistor here connects this cell
to the bit line if we put a stronger one
here because these are small inverters
we can defeat them so that even though
this inverter is trying to put a zero
here we defeat it with a one and then
what happens is now that this is a one
this inverter outputs a zero here this
inverter now starts outputting a one and
the cell becomes a one to make that
easier typically we have two of these
transistors and two bit lines for the
same cell that have the opposite values
so for this cell to become a one we put
one here and zero here that puts a one
here at the same time when we are
putting a zero here so these are more
easily defeated when we want to read we
can connect both of them to the bit
lines and if we wrote a one here we will
have this one be one this one be zero so
this line really outputs the bit we want
and this one just outputs the opposite
value of the bit we want by looking at
the difference between these bit lines
we can more quickly detect what the cell
actually has as we said these are weak
transistors here so once we connect this
cell to the bit lines the bit line is
long and in order to for example raise
the voltage on the bit line to a value
that corresponds to one these
transistors here are weak and cannot
pull it to one very fast they also will
try to lower this one down to zero and
they may not be able to do that very
fast so at the other end here where
we're trying to detect what in this cell
instead of looking at when will this
cross a threshold between a zero and a
one what we look at is in what direction
is the difference of these two going we
make them initially about halfway
between 0 and one we then activate the
word line the cell now starts let's say
pulling this one up and lowering this
one down if we look at what's the
difference very quickly we will detect
that this one here because it's drawn
towards one is getting to be larger
voltage than the voltage on this one so
we can now say that the cell had a one
before it actually manages to pull this
fully to one and lower this fully to
zero